<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Powerpoint on Avinash&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://avimallu.dev/tags/powerpoint/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Powerpoint on Avinash&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>© Avinash Mallya</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://avimallu.dev/tags/powerpoint/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Quick hacks to make client-ready presentations</title>
      <link>https://avimallu.dev/blog/003_powerpointsnap/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://avimallu.dev/blog/003_powerpointsnap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;premise&#34;&gt;Premise&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I worked in healthcare consulting, I often spent a LOT of my time creating PowerPoint presentations (&lt;em&gt;decks&lt;/em&gt; in consulting lingo - not even &lt;em&gt;slide decks&lt;/em&gt;). However, it was rather repetitive. Thus, was born PowerPointSnap.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-is-it&#34;&gt;What is it?&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll write this down as pointers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a VBA based PowerPoint add-on. Just a set of commands that work well with each other.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s Windows only - it&amp;rsquo;s unlikely to work on MacOS.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s installation-free and is not an executable, which makes it perfect for locked-down corporate environments, as long as you have the permission to download files.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-do-i-get-it&#34;&gt;How do I get it?&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The project is available on this &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/avimallu/PowerPointSnap&#34;&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;. The instructions to install it are available there, but here&amp;rsquo;s the down-low:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="premise">Premise</h1>
<p>When I worked in healthcare consulting, I often spent a LOT of my time creating PowerPoint presentations (<em>decks</em> in consulting lingo - not even <em>slide decks</em>). However, it was rather repetitive. Thus, was born PowerPointSnap.</p>
<h1 id="what-is-it">What is it?</h1>
<p>I&rsquo;ll write this down as pointers.</p>
<ol>
<li>It&rsquo;s a VBA based PowerPoint add-on. Just a set of commands that work well with each other.</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s Windows only - it&rsquo;s unlikely to work on MacOS.</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s installation-free and is not an executable, which makes it perfect for locked-down corporate environments, as long as you have the permission to download files.</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="how-do-i-get-it">How do I get it?</h1>
<p>The project is available on this <a href="https://github.com/avimallu/PowerPointSnap">Github repo</a>. The instructions to install it are available there, but here&rsquo;s the down-low:</p>
<ol>
<li>Download the Snap.ppam file to your system.</li>
<li>Enable the developer options.</li>
<li>Go to the Developer tab, and click on PowerPoint Add-ins.</li>
<li>Click on Add New. Choose the location of the file you just dowloaded. Click Close.</li>
<li>To uninstall, repeat the process, and simply click on Remove this time.</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="what-can-i-do-with-it">What can I do with it?</h1>
<p>Frankly, a LOT. The base concept of this tool is:</p>
<ol>
<li>&ldquo;Set&rdquo; a shape as the one you want to copy a property from.</li>
<li>Select any property from the list to automatically apply it.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a non-exhaustive list of all the options available.</p>
<h2 id="apply-properties-of-shapes-directly">Apply properties of shapes directly</h2>
<p>This is the part of the interface that can be used for shapes (which include charts and tables).</p>
<p><img src="/blog/003_powerpointsnap/01_Shapes.png" alt="The UI for copying shape properties"></p>
<p>To use, first select a <em>shape</em> object, click on &ldquo;Set&rdquo;. Then, choose the object you want to <em>Snap</em> its properties to (see how I got the inspiration for the name?). You should be able to copy all compatible properties - if something is not copy-able, the tool will show an error, and then let you exit.</p>
<p>Note that it&rsquo;s probably not to apply a property of a shape to a table - if you want to make the entire table orange, there are probably better built-in ways to do it than to use <em>Snap</em>.</p>
<h2 id="beautify-charts-with-snappable-properties">Beautify charts with <em>Snap</em>pable properties</h2>
<p>Charts are also supported, with dedicated features for it.</p>
<p><img src="/blog/003_powerpointsnap/02_Charts.png" alt="The UI for copying chart properties"></p>
<p>What do these features do? You should be able to hover over the option and get a tooltip that shows what it&rsquo;s capable of, but here&rsquo;s another summary just in case:</p>
<ol>
<li>Sync Value/Date Axis: this will try to align the range, the ticks, the numeric values etc. of the &ldquo;set&rdquo; chart to the one you&rsquo;ve selected. I couldn&rsquo;t put in just $x$ and $y$ here because Microsoft internally doesn&rsquo;t label them that way. Try either of these two options (you can undo!) and see what works best for your chart. This doesn&rsquo;t work well yet for 3D charts.</li>
<li>Sync Plot/Title/Legend: often, you want to centre a title, or make sure that multiple charts that show nearly identical things for different variables all <em>look</em> exactly the same from a client perspective. But that&rsquo;s usually difficult if you&rsquo;ve already configured the charts a little - which can be remedied with this option!</li>
<li>Format Painter: this is simply a helper for the normal format painter to align the formats of the text that you&rsquo;ve selected with the way it originally is in the &ldquo;set&rdquo; chart. The reason for this feature is simply to avoid going back to <em>Home</em> to click on the <em>Format Painter</em> option again.</li>
<li>Reset Axes Scales: in case you messed up somewhere, you can use this to rever to PowerPoint defaults.</li>
</ol>
<p>The next two options deserve their own section.</p>
<h2 id="customize-the-labels-programmatically">Customize the labels programmatically</h2>
<p>Your immediate senior in a consulting environment would frown at your chart, and then exclaim, &ldquo;I think that&rsquo;s too many labels for the data points. Can you show them every two/three/four labels? I know this is manual work, but it&rsquo;s a one time thing!&rdquo;</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s <strong>never</strong> a one time affair. But don&rsquo;t worry, we have this nice feature to help us. If you click on the <em>Customize Label</em> option, you will get this (without the &ldquo;Set&rdquo; option):</p>
<p><img src="/blog/003_powerpointsnap/DataLabelsScreenshot.JPG" alt="The UI for customizing labels."></p>
<p>Never mind the rather unfriendly legend entries. They&rsquo;re just here to demonstrate that you can do the following kinds of whacky abilities with your own chart!</p>
<h3 id="screenshots-of-the-chart-snapability">Screenshots of the chart <em>snap</em>ability</h3>
<p>Of course, visuals will do it more justice. For example, look at this image:</p>
<p><img src="/blog/003_powerpointsnap/Revenue_Presentation_1.png" alt="There’s a lot wrong with this image. But primarily, the charts are of different sizes, the axes are different, the labels are too clustered, and the titles aren’t centered."></p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s what you can do:</p>
<ol>
<li>Click on the left chart. Press &ldquo;Set&rdquo; in the toolbar for <em>Snap</em>.</li>
<li>Click on the right chart, and then go through the following:
<ol>
<li>In <em>Shapes</em>, click on <em>Dim</em>. This will align the shapes of the chart.</li>
<li>Use the guides that you get while moving the chart to align the positions of the two charts now that their shapes are equal.</li>
<li>You&rsquo;ll notice that the chart area doesn&rsquo;t still match, nor does the title.</li>
<li>In <em>Charts</em>, click on <em>Sync Plot Area</em> and <em>Sync Title Area</em>, and watch the magic unfold.</li>
<li>Now, click on the second chart, and click on &ldquo;Set&rdquo;. Let&rsquo;s align the axes of the first chart to the second one.</li>
<li>Click on the first chart, and then in <em>Charts</em>, click <em>Sync Value Axis</em>.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Let&rsquo;s bring that senior&rsquo;s exclamation back into play - (s)he wants you to highlight <em>only</em> Profit labels, and that too every 2 iterations. To do this:
<ol>
<li>Click on <em>Customize Labels</em> after clicking on either chart.</li>
<li>You&rsquo;ll get the screen shown in the previous section. Make sure to adjust the values such that it&rsquo;s exactly like the screenshot there.</li>
<li>Click on &ldquo;Save and Run&rdquo;. This will <em>save</em> the configuration you&rsquo;ve selected, and <em>run</em> it on the chart you&rsquo;ve selected.</li>
<li>Click the other chart. Then, in <em>Charts</em>, click on <em>Rerun Customization</em>.</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>
<p>This is what your results should look like:</p>
<p><img src="/blog/003_powerpointsnap/Revenue_Presentation_2.png" alt="Everything almost consistent. Your senior rests their eyes, and secretly wonder how you managed to do it quickly… maybe they should change some requirements…"></p>
<p>Of course, getting those calculations right is a whole different thing that will need some work.</p>
<h2 id="align-table-dimensions">Align table dimensions</h2>
<p>Oftentimes, you have two tables that show similar values&hellip; you know the drill. Here&rsquo;s what you can do in a scenario such as this:</p>
<p><img src="/blog/003_powerpointsnap/Table_Presentation_1.png" alt="Similar data, but vastly different tables."></p>
<p>This is what the <em>Tables</em> section of the tool looks like:</p>
<p><img src="/blog/003_powerpointsnap/03_Tables.png" alt="The UI for Tables"></p>
<p>To align these tables together,</p>
<ol>
<li>Click on the left table. Press &ldquo;Set&rdquo; in the toolbar for <em>Snap</em>.</li>
<li>Click on the right table.</li>
<li>Click on <em>Shapes</em>, inside it, <em>Dim</em>. Now the shapes of the table are the same.</li>
<li>In <em>Tables</em>, click on <em>Sync Column Widths</em>. Now the columns are also the same.</li>
<li>If you try to align by rows, it fails because the number of rows are not the same in the two tables.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here&rsquo;s what you&rsquo;ll end up with:</p>
<p><img src="/blog/003_powerpointsnap/Table_Presentation_2.png" alt="Similar data, and similar enough tables."></p>
<p>Pretty neat, eh?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
